Okay, בוקר
טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *daf* is צדי זין *Tzadi Zayin*, and
we pick up at the middle of צדי ו עמוד ב *Tzadi
Vav Amud Bet*. We had just done the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, which
had a whole case again about a
young adult, nine years and a day or more, before בר bar
מצוה *Bar Mitzvah*, that his act of sex with his sister-in-law counts
as a type of מאמר Maamar *Ma'amar*, but is not halachically יבום
yibum. *yibum*. And then it creates a scenario where if he then
does this with his sister-in-law and he dies, so for the next
brother, this sister-in-law is זיקת שני יבמים עליה *Zekat Shnei Yevamim Aleha*.
For the next brother, because there's still a מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום
Yibum *yibum* going back to the first her first husband, which has
never been actualized because what this underage man did did not count
as יבום Yibum, *yibum*. And then there's a מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום
Yibum. דרבנן *yibum derabbanan* that emerges from the second relationship, and therefore
in that situation, we don't allow יבום Yibum *yibum*, so we demand
for חליצה chalitzah *chalitzah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* starts with that
at the beginning of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* after the משנה Mishnah
*Mishna*, that eight lines down in the wide lines, six lines down
in the wide lines. אמר Amar, רבה הדה אמר רבנן זיקת שני
יבמים מחלץ חלץ יבמים לא מיבם *Amar Rabbah Hada Amar Rabbanan Zekat
Shnei Yevamim Mechelatz Chaletz Yebamim Lo Meyabbem*. The rabbinic idea that somebody
that a woman that has these two brother-in-law זיקות *zekot* on her,
like the scenario we spoke about, that you do חליצה Chalitzah, *chalitzah*
not יבום Yibum *yibum*. לא תימא היכא דאיכא צרה *Lo Teima Heicha
De'ika Tzara*. Don't say that that was just like the case we
saw not in our פרק perek *Perek*, but in an earlier פרק
perek *Perek*, when there is a co-wife. דאיכא למיגזר משום צרה *De'ika
Lemigzar Mishum Tzara*, that the reason has to do with the co-wife.
הכא *Hacha*, in our case, ליכא צרה *leka tzara*, there is no
co-wife, and זיקת שני יבמים מחלץ חלץ יבמים לא מיבם *Zekat Shnei
Yevamim Mechelatz Chaletz Yebamim Lo Meyabbem*, and it's the same הלכה halacha
*halacha* חליצה Chalitzah. *chalitzah* not יבום Yibum *yibum*. So what is he
talking about? Well, in our case, where I gave the ער *Er*,
אונן *Onan*, and שלה *Shelah* example, ער *Er* dies, אונן *Onan* as
an underage קטן katan, *kattan* does ביאה biah *bi'ah* with her, and
therefore it's a type of a דרבנן *derabbanan* marriage but not יבום
Yibum דאורייתא de-oraisa *yibum de'oraita*, that's sort of like a מאמר Maamar
*ma'amar*. And then אונן *Onan* dies. So שלה *Shelah*'s obligation to תמר
*Tamar* is דאורייתא *de'oraita* from ער *Er*, because ער *Er* was really
married to her. And a separate one that is דרבנן *derabbanan* from
אונן *Onan*, because אונן *Onan* was sort of like quasi-married to her.
Now, if אונן *Onan* was דאורייתא *de'oraita* married to her, it would
have removed ער *Er* from the picture. But since it's not דאורייתא
*de'oraita*, since it's only this type of a rabbinic and this זיקה
zika. *zekah* type of a thing, ער *Er* is still in the
picture and אונן *Onan* is in the picture, so she has two
זיקות *zekot* on תמר *Tamar*, one from ער *Er* and one from
אונן *Onan*, and the הלכה halacha *halacha* is you do חליצה Chalitzah.
*chalitzah* and not יבום Yibum. *yibum*. And here there is no co-wife.
That's what רבה *Rabbah* means, in our case there's no co-wife. What
is the case of a co-wife that I might have limited it
to?
The case of a co-wife would have been let's just do it
different anyway. Would have been that they're all adults, right, and he
goes ahead and he's married and then he dies. She's the wife.
He does מאמר Maamar *ma'amar*.
So that's the parallel to the קטן katan *kattan* doing ביאה bi'ah
*bi'ah*, right? He does מאמר Maamar, *ma'amar* and he's also married to
another woman. Okay, so wife two. And then he dies. In this
case, I mean, yeah, you could have just said אונן *Onan* is
married to צפורה *Tziporah*, but okay. In this case, he cannot have
to do חליצה Chalitzah *chalitzah* and not יבום Yibum *yibum*. Why do
we have to do חליצה Chalitzah, *chalitzah* and not יבום Yibum. *yibum*
in this case? Remember, he can really do יבום Yibum *yibum* because
of the זיקה zika *zekah* of number one, דאורייתא *de'oraita* speaking. Anything
that's going to say other, right, is going to be only because
of like a rabbinic rule that she's also rabbinically two's wife and
therefore as a result of that, this case of two זיקות *zekot*,
do חליצה Chalitzah *chalitzah* not יבום Yibum *yibum*. Why here would be
what would be the concern here? The concern is if we allow
him to do יבום Yibum *yibum* here, right, he might also decide,
and this is really because of her relationship to one, he might
also go ahead and decide to do יבום yibum. *yibum* here. And
then from people's perspective, it looks like he's done יבום yibum? *yibum*
with two wives of number two. And that's not allowed. People won't
realize that this יבום yibum. *yibum* is really because of the זיקה
*zekah* of number one. So יבום yibum. *yibum* with one חליצה Chalitzah
*chalitzah* with the other. So the answer is, right, why not do
יבום yibum *yibum* with one and חליצה Chalitzah *chalitzah* with the other?
Why do you demand that you do חליצה Chalitzah *chalitzah* here? Why
not חליצה chalitzah *chalitzah* there and יבום yibum *yibum* here? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discusses it. But the point is, this concern when
there's a co-wife and it'll appear weird is what leads to us
putting restrictions on this case. רבה *Rabbah* says don't think that that's
the only time we put restrictions because here there's no co-wife and
we're also saying just do חליצה chalitzah *chalitzah* don't do יבום yibum
*yibum*. Okay, so that's the point that רבה *Rabbah* is making. This
is an obvious case we want to try to control because of
appearances with the co-wife, but we're even going to put restrictions on
this case. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. נשא
אשה nasa isha? ומת *Nasa Isha Vemet*. Now if this קטן katan,
*kattan* did not a יבום yibum *yibum*, but we just with a
normal woman did קידושין Kiddushin ונישואין *Kiddushin and Nisuin*, there is no
status to that and if he dies, the woman does not have
to do anything חליצה chalitzah, *chalitzah* with the brothers. תנינא להא דתנו
רבנן *Tanina Leha De'tano Rabbanan*. That was taught by our rabbis. שוטה
shoteh, וקטן, a שוטה, somebody who is not of right mind, and
a minor, שנשאו ומתו, shenasu umetu, even if they did נישואין Nissuin
and died, נשותיהם פטורות מן החליצה ומן היבום, neshoteihem peturot min hachalitzah
umin hayibum, their wives are exempt from חליצה chalitzah or יבום. yibum
It's not recognized legally at all. Of course, this has two out
of the classic
three. Normally there's חרש. cheresh. As the גמרא Gemara said, actually the
rabbis did institute קידושין and נישואין Nissuin for a חרש, cheresh, at
least rabbinically. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. בן תשע שנים
שהגיע. Ben tesha shanim shehiggia.
Now this guy who's nine years old, he did this case with
Tamar, and he's also married to Devorah. And now he becomes an
adult. So if he consummates his relationship with Tamar now that he's
an adult, then he's genuinely married to both wives. If he didn't
consummate it, then we've got the case that we've been dealing with.
Okay, and what's the consequence of that situation if he didn't consummate?
If he
didn't, thank you, if he didn't consummate it, so then as far
as Devorah's concerned, that's a real wife of Onan. Do what you
want, do יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitza right? Because that's a real
wife of Onan. As far as Tamar's concerned, just do חליצה. chalitza
Sorry, he did not. He did not consummate it with Tamar. Okay,
he did not consummate it with Tamar. So Sheila is told, oh,
Devorah is a real wife and a real mitzvah of יבום, yibum
you could do יבום. yibum, Tamar was only rabbinic, you have to
do חליצה. chalitza, The reason we don't say this is sufficient, just
do יבום yibum and you're done, which is what we would normally
say, is because Tamar really is still linked to Er, and it
hasn't really finished, you know, finished that whole thing with Er. There
hasn't been a יבום yibum or a חליצה based on her marriage
to Er. Right? Is everybody sort of clear on this? So therefore
we say, as we said, Tamar who did this weird case only
do חליצה, Devorah, if you want to, you could do יבום with
her. That's what the משנה mishnah says. Yes? No, no, I mean
say. Like how do we get to know he died, right? How
do we know if he consummated it? We assume like for a
year he did it, for a month? Yeah, that's a good question.
I don't know. Maybe there was a way to be נשא אשה?
Yeah, it's a good question. We ask her maybe? I don't know.
All right. So... How do you have to wait three months to
see if she's pregnant? Maybe you do. Let's not worry about that
now. Okay, so it says like this.
Okay, so come on. Shh. יעשו. Ya'asu. The גמרא Gemara says like
this.
ביאת בן תשע כמאמר בגדול Biat ben tesha kemamar begadol ותחלוץ צרה
מיבום. vetechlotz tzara miyibum. And what do we say happens? Remember this
case, what happened when we said two did מאמר Maamar. with this
woman and then he died? We said three have to do,
actually I didn't tell you this, but what we said before if
you remember is not only can he not do יבום with this
woman, we actually say that he has to do חליצה with both
women. We don't let them do any יבום. So the גמרא Gemara
said, wait a minute, this is exactly parallel to this case. This
is the ביאה bi'ah of a קטן, katan, this is the מאמר
ma'amar, of a גדול, gadol, and here we're saying yes, חליצה with
Tamar, that was the point we made first, okay, חליצה with Tamar
even though there's no co-wife, but we're allowing him to do יבום
with Devorah. Why is that? In this case we demand חליצה with
both wives. So let's take a look. So the גמרא gemara says
like this. אמר רב
אשי, Amar Rav Ashi,
okay, אמר רב, Amar Rav, לא עשו ביאת בן תשע כמאמר בגדול.
Lo asu biat ben tesha kemamar begadol.
All right, they didn't make it totally. Until now we've been saying
they have. They have to a certain degree, enough certainly to disqualify
the brothers and other types of implications that we've been dealing with,
but it's not so powerful to push Devorah out of the picture.
And so because it's weaker and maybe not perceived as real or
whatever, Devorah is not pushed out of the picture and Sheila can
still do יבום. All right, so that's what רב Rav says. ושמואל
אמר עשו ועשו. Ushmuel amar asu vaasu. No, it is just as
good as מאמר בגדול. Maamar begadol. So then the question is why
is it not the same? So we'll get to that in a
bit. וכן אמר רבי יוחנן עשו ועשו. Vechen amar Rabbi Yochanan asu
vaasu. It's just as good as מאמר בגדול. Maamar begadol. והא יעשו,
Veha ya'asu, but that question of, let's not, now this יעשו ya'asu
is funny. It doesn't mean let's make the act of the ביאת
הקטן biat hakatan like מאמר בגדול. Maamar begadol. Here יעשו ya'asu means
in terms of the implications of what happens in this case when
there is מאמר ma'amar, or ביאת קטן biat katan and a co-wife,
that is תנאי היא. tannai hi. That's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim.
הך תנא דארבעה אחים, Hach tanna de'arba achim,
and תנא tanna of this case, which was a משנה mishnah in
the פרק ארבעה אחים, Perek Arba Achim, okay, גזר משום צרה. gazar
mishum tzara.
He's concerned that we don't let him do יבום with this one
because then he'll do יבום with this one anyway because of this
case of the co-wife, we don't let any יבום take place. ואשמעינן
בגדול, Veashme'inan begadol,
and it told us the case of an adult who's doing מאמר,
ma'amar that husband number two was an adult who did מאמר. ma'amar,
והוא הדין בקטן. Vehua hadin bekatan. But you know what? This תנא
tanna that says that you have to do חליצה with both. wives,
would say here too with the קטן katan you have to do
חליצה with both wives. Nobody is distinguishing. There's a מחלוקת תנאים machloket
tanna'im what's the story with wife number two. Okay, in this case
of זיקה שני יבמים, zika sheni yevamim, this earlier משנה mishnah said,
wife number two also has חליצה, and our משנה mishnah says, wife
number two you could do יבום. It just so happens that he's
talking about a case of a גדול, gadol, he's talking about a
case of a קטן, katan but that's not the debate. It doesn't
matter גדול gadol or קטן, katan the debate is, do you have
to do חליצה with wife number two or can you do יבום?
But our משנה mishnah. doesn't apply to this, it's חולצת או מתייבמת,
choletzet o mityabemet, right? You're allowed to do יבום. No, but did
he say only, or you have to do? According to this author
of this משנה mishnah is not the author of that משנה. mishnah.
Right. So the author of this משנה mishna, would have a different
ruling in our משנה. mishna Okay. So הכא תנא דבי אחין גזר
משום צרה, haka tana d'vei achin gazar mishum tzara, ואשמעינן בגדול, v'ashmiunan
b'gadol, והוא הדין בקטן, v'hu hadin b'katan,
even in a case of a minor, you would not be able
to do יבום. והאי דאמר גדול, v'hai d'amar gadol,
why did he give the example of גדול? gadol? משום דבגדול קאי,
mishum d'v'gadol kai, he's dealing with a גדול. gadol. והאי תנא דהכא,
v'hai tanna d'hacha, and our תנא tanna סבירא ליה לא אסרו, svira
lei lo asru, ולא גזר משום צרה, v'lo gazar mishum tzara,
he feels that, yes, the ביאה bi'ah, of a קטן is just
as strong as the מאמר, but even though the ביאה of a
קטן is just as strong as the מאמר, he's not making a
גזירה, gezeirah, he's not concerned to prevent יבום from the other wife.
ואשמעינן בגדול, v'ashmiunan b'gadol, and he says that you can do יבום
with the other wife, he happens to be talking about a case
of ביאת קטן, biat katan, והוא הדין בגדול, v'hu hadin b'gadol, and
but it would same be true if there was if the second
husband was an adult and did מאמר and then he died, you'd
still be allowed to do יבום with the co-wife. והאי דקתני בקטן
דבקטן קאי, v'hai d'katani b'katan d'v'katan kai, so why is he giving
the case of קטן because that's what we've been talking about, which
is a very interesting answer, although the most obvious difference between these
two cases is this is an adult and this is a minor,
and you would think that that leads to the difference in דין,
din, points no, they actually would say the same הכי תאמר hachi
tomar the same הלכה halakhic by a minor with ביאה, and he'd
say the same הלכה with an adult by מאמר, and they're actually
just debating whether you're allowed to do יבום with the co-wife or
not. Okay. Now, אזל רבי אלעזר אמר לשמעתא בי מדרשא. azal Rabbi
Elazar amar l'shma'ata bei midrasha.
So רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, so this was רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan
way of explaining this seeming the contradiction of the two משניות, mishnayot,
was explaining it by saying yeah, they actually are debating this point.
Okay. Anyway, so רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, his student, went and told
over this discussion in the בית מדרש beit midrash and pointed out
the problem, pointed out the resolution or framing it as a debate,
ולא אמרה משמיה דרבי יוחנן, v'lo amrah mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan, but he
didn't say that this was what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. שמע
רבי יוחנן ואיקפד. shama Rabbi Yochanan v'ikpad. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan heard
and he took umbrage, he took offense that his whole תורה Torah
was being taught over but not in his name. עול לגבי רבי
אמי ורבי אסי. ul l'gabei Rabbi Ami v'Rabbi Assi.
So רבי אמי Rabbi Ami ורבי אסי Rabbi Assi came to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to try to calm him down and appease him
and make him not so angry at his student רבי אלעזר. Rabbi
Elazar. אמרו ליה, amru lei, they said to him, לאו כך היה
המעשה בבית הכנסת של טבריא, lav kach hayah hama'aseh b'veit haknesset shel
Tverya, one minute, he says, look, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it's not
a good idea to get too upset and to get into a
fight. Remember what happened in that synagogue in Tiberias בנגר שיש בראשו
גלוסטרא, b'nagar sheyesh b'rosho glustra,
there's a whole debate, there's a whole case about are you allowed
to use a like doorstopper, not a doorstopper, a what's the thing,
a bar, you know, that goes through the
whole a bolt, right? You know like when you bolt your door
at the top. So you had a bolt that's hanging from the
door, and when you put it in to lock the door, is
that like a type of a rabbinic בניין? binyan? And is there
a מוקצה muktzah type of a problem the whole thing? So if
the bolt, the big you know thick thing, has like a bulb
at the top and could be used for like grinding things, it's
more of a כלי kli and therefore it's less of a בניין
binyan type of a concern, and that was the discussion. When you've
got that type of a bolt, are you allowed to put it
in the door on שבת? Shabbat? Is this רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami, and רבי אסי? Rabbi Assi? No, I think
they're his students. Yeah, I think so. Okay. בנגר שיש בראשו גלוסטרא,
b'nagar sheyesh b'rosho glustra, so they were dealing with this bolt that
has this bulb on it, שנחלקו בו רבי אלעזר ורבי יוסי, shenechleku
bo Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Yose, and they were having a whole debate
about it in the שול shul that whether you're allowed to do
it on שבת Shabbat or not allowed to do it on שבת,
Shabbat, עד שקרעו ספר תורה בחמתן, ad shekar'u sefer Torah b'chamatan, they
ripped the ספר תורה sefer Torah in their anger, they got so
worked up. So first of all the גמרא gemara interjects: קרעו סלקא
דעתך? kar'u salka datchach? What? They intentionally ripped the ספר תורה? sefer
Torah? אלא שנקרע ספר תורה בחמתן. ela shenikra sefer Torah b'chamatan.
Okay,
it wasn't intentional, but somehow they got into such a fight, who
knows, the ספר תורה sefer Torah fell off the בימה bimah and
it ripped. Alright. והיה שם רבי יוסי בן קיסמא, v'hayah sham Rabbi
Yose ben Kisma, רבי יוסי בן קיסמא Rabbi Yose ben Kisma was
there ואמר תמיה אני אם לא יהיה בית הכנסת זו עבודה זרה.
v'amar tmei'ani im lo yihyeh beit haknesset zu avodah zarah. I would
be astounded, this is so terrible, this is so undermining about the
sanctity of the קדושת בית הכנסת kedushat beit haknesset and you know
מחלוקת לשם שמים machloket l'shem shamayim that it could lead to this
type of anger or whatever, that this שול, shul, I would be
astounded if it would not become a house of idolatry. Okay, it
should be like בית עבודה זרה. beit avodah zarah. וכן הוה, v'chein
havah, and that happened, the שול shul was, you know, somehow destroyed
and on its place was rebuilt a house of idolatry. So he
says, hey, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it's not a good idea to
get so worked up over when you know... והיה שם רבי יוסי
בן קיסמא, v'hayah sham Rabbi Yose ben Kisma, that too also. Anyway,
so they were basically just telling him, calm down. calm down. Now
as you know, somebody's angry and say, "Calm down, calm down, calm
down," it never does any good, it just gets the person angrier.
So, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. הדר Hadar איקפד
ikpeid זינא zina אחרינא achrina more angry! And
why did he get more angry? אמר, חברותא chavrusa נמי? nami? What,
you're making me like their, like you know, Rabbi Eliezer's חברותא? chavrusa?
Because that was a debate of colleagues, of peers, right? That was
a debate of Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yose. So you're saying, ah,
you look, you know, he's just got that, whatever, he's not my
colleague, he's my student, and I have a right to be angry
at him. Okay, ולגבי ulegabai Rabbi Yaakov בר אידי. Idi. So Rabbi
Yaakov bar Idi then went to visit Rabbi Yochanan and he gave
it a try. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, כאשר
צוה ה' את משה, ka'asher tzivah Hashem es Moshe, this is a
פסוק pasuk in יהושע. Yehoshua. כאשר צוה ה' את משה עבדו כן
צוה משה את יהושע וכן עשה יהושע, ka'asher tzivah Hashem es Moshe
avdo kein tzivah Moshe es Yehoshua vechein asah Yehoshua,
and Yehoshua did likewise. לא הסיר
דבר מכל אשר צוה ה' את משה. lo hesir davar mikol asher
tzivah Hashem es Moshe. So, so here's the question he asked. He
said to Rabbi Yochanan, what do you think happened when Yehoshua taught
over some תורה? Torah? וכי על כל דבר שאמר יהושע היה אומר
להם כך אמר לי משה? vechi al kol davar she'amar Yehoshua hayah
omer lahem kach amar li Moshe? Every single time Yehoshua said something,
he said, here's what Moshe said, here's what Moshe said, here's what
Moshe said. You think Yehoshua actually said that? No! אלא יהושע יושב
ודורש סתם, ela Yehoshua yoshev vedoresh stam,
Yehoshua would just teach תורה, Torah, והכל יודעים שתורתו של משה היא.
vehakol yod'im sheToraso shel Moshe hi. Of course it would be known
that he got all this from Moshe. So the fact that the
תורה Torah underscores, the פסוק pasuk in יהושע Yehoshua underscores so much
that he- that everything he got from Moshe he gave over, he
was the total like עבד נאמן eved ne'eman and תלמיד נאמן talmid
ne'eman of Moshe, meant that he didn't have to much explicitly label
that what he was doing was from Moshe 'cause it was so
clear that that- that he was just the channel, you know, and
the- what Moshe had essentially. So, right, it's-
that is a nice answer because it speaks to Rabbi Yochanan's pride
and concern, right? So as opposed to just saying, don't get so
angry. Okay, so, okay. אף רבי אלעזר תלמידך יושב ודורש סתם. Af
Rabbi Elazar talmidcha yoshev vedoresh stam.
Yes,
it's true, he doesn't mention your name. But why? והכל יודעים ששלך
היא. Vehakol yod'im sheshelcha hi. No- very sensitive! Everybody knows where he
gets his תורה Torah from. All right. אמר להם, Amar lahem, מפני
מה אין אתם יודעין לפייס כבן אידי חברינו? mipnei mah ein atem
yod'in lepayeis keben Idi chaveireinu? Ah, he says, you know, he said
to the first two, why didn't you know how to appease me
as well as Ben Idi here does? He knows how to calm
daddy down, there's no reason to stay angry at the first two
guys. Yeah, okay. Rabbi Yochanan, now Rabbi Yochanan,
yeah, I don't know though, it sounds like חברינו chaveireinu sounds like
they were colleagues here, not students. I'm not sure about that. Rabbi
Yochanan, מאי טעמא קפיד כולי האי? mai ta'ama kapeid kulei hai? Now
why did Rabbi Yochanan get so upset? דאמר רבי יהודה אמר רב,
De'amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav, מאי דכתיב, mai dechsiv, what's meant by
the פסוק, pasuk, אגורה באהלך
עולמים? agurah be'aholcha olamim? It says David will live in your tent
forever. וכי אפשר לאדם לגור בשני עולמים? Vechi efshar le'adam lagur bishnei
olamim? עולמים Olamim is in plural, two worlds. וכי אפשר לאדם לגור
בשני עולמים? Vechi efshar le'adam lagur bishnei olamim? Can you live in
two worlds, this world and the world- and the world to come?
אלא אמר דוד, like the heavenly world, you know, which is where
you go after you die. אלא אמר דוד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא,
ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel olam, יהי רצון yehi ratzon מלפניך milfanecha
שיאמרו דבר שמועה מפי בעולם הזה. sheyomru davar shemuah mipi ba'olam hazeh.
That even after I die and I'm living in the heavenly world,
that people tell over my teaching in this world. דאמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי, De'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai, because David said quoting Rabbi Yochanan in the name of Rabbi
Shimon ben Yochai, כל תלמיד חכם שאומרים דבר שמועה מפיו בעולם הזה
שפתותיו דובבות בקבר. kol talmid chacham she'omrim davar shemuah mipi ba'olam hazeh
siftosav dovvos bakever. Any תלמיד חכם talmid chacham that they say over
his תורה Torah in his name in this world, his lips will
continue to like murmur in the grave. It's like you're keeping the
person alive, and you're keeping it by keeping their תורה Torah alive,
you're keeping that person alive. ואמר רבי יצחק בן זעירא, Ve'amar Rabbi
Yitzchak ben Zeira, and therefore he's also living in two worlds, he's
alive in this- we- continues to be alive in this world 'cause
his lips are moving and it's like he's alive, while he's living
in the world to come. אמר רבי יצחק בן זעירא ואיתימא רבי
שמעון נזירא, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak ben Zeira ve'iseima Rabbi Shimon Nezira, מאי
קרא, mai kra, what's the פסוק? pasuk? וחכך כיין הטוב הולך לדודי
למישרים דובב שפתי ישנים, vechicheich kiyayin hatov holeich ledodi lemeisharim doveiv sifsei
yeshenim, which seems unquestionably the פסוק pasuk that they were having in
mind when they said that, right? So it's like, you know, his-
his jowl is like the good wine, you know, going like straight
away. It
murmurs... דובב שפתי ישנים, doveiv sifsei yeshenim, right. I'm sorry, I already
read it with the- with the פשט... pshat... ישנים, yeshenim, right, okay.
The flowing or whatever of the, you know, of ancient lips, ככומר
של ענבים, kechomer shel anavim, it's like a press of grapes. מה
כומר של ענבים כיון שמניח אדם אצבעו עליו, mah chomer shel anavim
kivan shemaniach adam etzba'o alav, as soon as a person puts his
finger, the grapes have already been pressed, as soon as you touch
them, מיד דובב, miyad doveiv, immediately they start to flow. אף תלמידי
חכמים כיון שאומרים דבר שמועה מפיהם, af talmidei chachamim kivan she'omrim davar
shemuah mipihem, as soon as you start saying over their תורה, Torah,
so שפתותיהם דובבות בקבר, siftoseihem dovvos bakever, their lips start murmuring in
the grave. And therefore Rabbi Yochanan, you know, the גמרא Gemara's is
saying, he wasn't doing it out of an issue of pride, but,
you know, part of his- what he leaves behind- is going to
be leaving behind in this world is his תורה, Torah, right? Part
of his- and therefore, you know, that's part of his sense of
like, you know, keeping alive and stuff, alive in this world is
that his תורה Torah is kept alive. kept alive in his name,
and therefore and therefore he was מקפיד *makpid*. So again David was
quoting not only רב יוחנן *Reb Yochanan*, רב שמעון בר יוחאי *Reb
Shimon bar Yochai*, he was also quoting his son שלמה *Shlomo*'s פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* in שיר השירים *Shir Hashirim*, anyway. Alright, and of course
whenever I read this or something like this, I always like quoting
Woody Allen who says, I don't want to be made immortal through
my work, I want to be immortal through not dying.
It's interesting that they quoted an actual name of a פרק perek
*perek* before. Does the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* usually do that? It does
do that sometimes. No, I know, sometimes, but usually does it generally
have פרקים *perakim*? פרקים *perakim* they had, sure. I mean they didn't
have the פרק perek *perek* divided into משניות *Mishnayot*, but רבי *Rebbi*
but certainly I mean I think I've never seen anybody question the
idea that already from the time of רבי *Rebbi* it was divided
into פרקים *perakim*. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אחד
בן תשע שנים *Echad ben tesha shanim*, so whether this idea of
the of the ביאה *biah* of a קטן *katan* is like a
מאמר *maamar*, the משנה mishna *Mishnah* says it's whether he's a קטן
*katan* or even if he's an adult and he's twenty years old
if he hasn't had pubic hairs, halachically he's still a קטן *katan*.
So says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, ורמינהו *u'reminhu* I'll ask you on
this, בן עשרים שנה שלא הביא שתי שערות *ben esrim shana shelo
hevi shtei searos*, if you have a twenty-year-old who has not had
pubic hair, יביאו ראיה raya. שהוא בן עשרים והוא הסריס *yaviu reaya
shehu ben esrim vehu hasaris*, bring proof that he's twenty and if
he's already twenty and no pubic hair, that proves that he's the
סריס *saris* that the רבנן *Rabbanan* spoke about. לא חולץ ולא v'lo
מיבם *Lo choletz velo meyabem*, and he's completely, as opposed to somebody
who's just sterile because this is something about his body never having
reached maturity, he's totally out of the category and he doesn't do
חליצה *chalitzah* and יבום *yibbum*, and therefore the cases of the משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* wouldn't apply because the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* is waiting for
the minor to become an adult to consummate, the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*
assumes that the act of sex of a קטן *katan* counts as
a מאמר *maamar*, presumably the act of sex of a סריס *saris*
would not count as anything because he's completely out of the category
of חליצה *chalitzah* and יבום *yibbum*. So you see that this person
once he's twenty he's out of the category, he's no longer like
a קטן *katan*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אביי *Abaye* oh
no, and then it continues, בת עשרים שנה שלא הביאה שתי שערות
*bas esrim shana shelo hevia shtei searos*, similarly by a woman twenty
years old who hasn't had pubic hair, תביא ראיה שהיא בת עשרים
והיא האילונית *tavi reaya shehi bas esrim vehi ha-aylonis*, and if once
it's proved that she's twenty and she hasn't had physical maturity then
she's the category of אילונית *aylonis*, לא חולצת ולא מתייבמת *lo choletzes
velo misyabemes*, also similarly completely out of the category. So that's against
our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. Our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says that he's still
treated as a קטן *katan*, and which means he's still somewhat in
the category. So הא איתמר עלה *ha itmar alah*, what was said
about this, אמר רב שמואל בר יצחק *amar Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak*,
so here's the resolution, אמר רב *amar Rav*, והוא שנולדו לו סימני
סריס *vehu shenoldu lo simanei saris*. No, it's not enough to be
twenty and not have pubic hair, the person also has to have
certain other indicators that he's a סריס *saris*, and we discussed what
those indicators were if you remember a few weeks ago. אמר רבא
דיקא נמי דקתני והוא הסריס *Amar Rava deika nami d'katani vehu hasaris*,
because it says and he is the saris, somehow it seems to
be indicating that there's other indicators about that, not exactly clear why
but anyway, שמע מינה *shma mina*. So okay, so our משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah* he's twenty, he's still treated as a קטן *katan* and he's
still somewhat in the category because he doesn't have these other characteristics.
But when he has these other characteristics and he's twenty and he
doesn't have pubic hair, then he's the סריס *saris*. וכי לא נולדו
לו סימני סריס עד כמה *Vechi lo noldu lo simanei saris ad
kama*, and now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if he never gets
these other characteristics at what age will you say that he might
still be able to achieve
physiological biological
maturity? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* can't imagine that this person is not
at one stage in his life going to be a סריס *saris*,
if he's never going to achieve that pubic hair and those types
of stages of maturity. So at what age would you say it
even without those other signs? So תני דבי רבי חייא *Tani d'bei
Rebbi Chiya*, עד רוב שנותיו *ad rov shnotav*, once he hits the
majority of his years, which is assumed, how are we going to
know? Which is assumed like seventy years is assumed to be the
lifespan and therefore once he hits like thirty-six, then he's considered a
סריס *saris*, even without other indicators. כי אתו לקמיה דרבא *Ki asu
lakamei de'Rava*, so when somebody like this would come to רבא *Rava*
and it looked like he would be a סריס *saris* and he
didn't get again have pubic hair, if the person was very lean,
meaning underfed, אמר להו זילו אבריוהו *amar lehu zilu avriyuhu*, רבא
*Rava* would say before we make any decision about him, go feed
him, get him stronger, maybe the reason that his body hasn't matured
is because he is undernourished. איברי *Ibari*,
but they find this right in developing
countries, about undernourished kids or whatever, now people don't know what I'm
talking about, right? Right, like not having women not menstruating, we find
that in the United States with very
poorly fed women don't have menstrual periods and gymnasts and stuff like
that. Yes. Interesting. Okay. ואי ברי *Ve'ei bari*, and if the guy
was maybe a little bit too healthy, meaning a little bit too
fat, אמר להו זילו אכחישוהו *amar lehu zilu achchishuhu*, go put him
on an exercise regimen, דהני סימני זימנין דנפלי מחמת כחישותא וזימנין דנפלי
מחמת בריותא *d'hanei simanei zimnin d'nafli machamat kachishusa vezimnin d'nafli machamat briyusa*,
because these pubic hair
sometimes they fall off or maybe don't come as a result of
being
underfed, sometimes they come as a result of being a little bit
too fat. Okay, הדרן עלך האישה רבה *Hadran Alach Ha'isha Rabba*. So
that was the end of that פרק *perek* which was a fascinating
and challenging פרק *perek* about the woman whose husband returned from far
away, and then we dealt with the wife who the husband whose
wife returned from far away and then in the end we got
back to straight יבום *yibbum* discussions and particularly around this case. about
the underage young man who is doing ביאה. Now we move on
and it's very it gets you a little dizzy like what was
it what is the topic? You know keep on going back and
forth so now we are back to not יבום but discussions about
relatives and marrying relatives of some degree or another, which is issues
that obviously we did touch around before, particularly about the husband that
married his wife's sister. So this seems to now be picking up
on that theme, נושאין על האנוסה. Nosein al ha-Anusa. So yes, can
I ask you just like a naive question, why is it just
called האשה רבה? Ha-Isha Raba? Because there's another פרק of האשה Ha-Isha
that's smaller, but it's a good question. It's not the big woman.
It just dawned upon me. Yes, yes, so they do so פרק
at the end is called האשה שלום. Ha-Isha Shalom. So there's האשה
רבה Ha-Isha Raba to distinguish it from the other פרק of האשה.
Ha-Isha. So unlike the norm in which it's simply the first words
of the משנה, Mishnah they added the האשה Ha-Isha because there are
two האשהs. Ha-Isha Editorial comments on yeah, I mean I don't know
when exactly the names emerged or whatever, but right, the ראשונים Rishonim
definitely were already calling it האשה רבה Ha-Isha Raba to distinguish it
from a later פרק which is also האשה Ha-Isha and called האשה
שלום. Ha-Isha Shalom. But yes, thank you. נושאין על האנוסה. Nosein al
ha-Anusa. So you can marry a woman who is related to you
only because of an act of rape ועל המפותה ve-al ha-mefuta or
an act of seduction, which basically means, right, let's take the case
about, you know, wife's sister. So let's say, right, which is the
case we dealt with before, let's say you didn't marry this Rachel,
but this person had sex with Rachel, okay, without marriage, what for
the גמרא Gemara sex without marriage is going to be labeled as
אנוסה Anusa or מפותה, Mefuta, rape or seduction. So therefore in that
case he can marry Leah, okay, because it's only that's an איסור,
issur, איסורים issurim that have to do with a relationship to one's
wife, which are basically two, but you could call it three or
three you could call it two, is wife's sister, wife's mother, and
wife's daughter, okay, because mother and daughter are like flip sides of
the same coin. All of those things that have to do with
the relationship to my wife says the משנה Mishnah are because they're
related to your wife, not because they're related to the woman you
slept with. Okay, so that's נושאין על האנוסה. Nosein al ha-Anusa. You
can marry a woman if the first relationship wasn't one of marriage
but the first relationship was one of just having an act of
sex ועל המפותה. ve-al ha-mefuta. In other words, the movie The Graduate.
Yeah, okay. האונס והמפתה על האנוסה חייב, Ha-oneis ve-ha-mefateh al ha-anusa chayav,
but the reverse is not true. A man is married to a
woman and he doesn't marry the woman's sister, he just sleeps with
the woman's sister, or he doesn't marry the woman's mother or daughter,
he just sleeps with them. That is the biblical prohibition. So it
starts with a man's wife, and then it's don't sleep with her
sister, mother, daughter, okay, but it starts with the woman being the
man's wife, not being a woman the man slept with. נושא אדם
אנוסת אביו ומפוטת אביו. Nosei adam anusat aviv u-mefutat aviv.
Now that's as I said about wife, wife's mother, daughter, sister. What
about father? What about a woman that a man's father slept with
out of marriage? So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that's not
your mother, it's not your stepmother, so that's מותר, mutar, a woman
your father slept with. אנוסת בנו ומפוטת בנו. Anusat beno u-mefutat beno.
Similarly, there's
a
prohibition of sleeping with your daughter-in-law even after, you know, your son
died or divorced her. But she had to have been your daughter-in-law.
She had to have been married to your son. Let's say it
was a woman your son slept with. That's not prohibited. Okay, so
the same way relationships to one's wife, wife's sister, mother, daughter is
only if there was a wife, you only after you married her,
relationship to one's stepmother and stepdaughter is similarly only if there was
a stepmother, stepdaughter, there was a marriage to father or son. If
it was just father or son sleeping with them, it would not
be. That's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. רבי יהודה אוסר באנוסת אביו
ומפוטת אביו. Rabbi Yehuda oser be-anusat aviv u-mefutat aviv. You might remember
this, we dealt with it a number of times earlier, that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the one case he makes an exception about
is father. A woman that a man's father had slept with even
if not a stepmother is forbidden to that man. Yes. Isn't there
some פסוק pasuk about the fathers and sons were sleeping with the
same woman? Yeah, there's פסוקים psukim in yeah, איש ואביו, ish ve-aviv,
what is it? Some אביו aviv whatever ילכו אל הנערה למען חלל
את שם קדשי yelchu el ha-na’ara lema’an challel et shem kodshi in
Amos, right, the prophet. Yeah, but right, so that's right, that's a
basic statement of, as exactly you say, about a decay of morality,
not necessarily whether it's a technical עריות. arayot. But it's an interesting
point. You're right. Like oh, okay, well, if somebody comes with like
a pure halakhic perspective, oh, I don't understand, what's the איסור? issur?
Why is the prophet upset? Right? But yeah, the פסוק pasuk, is
talking about like, you know, exactly about how like, you know, lack
of any shame and the decay of morality and all of that,
even though it's not a technical איסור. issur. It's an excellent point.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, תנינא מלתא דתנו רבנן.
Tnina miltah de-tanu rabanan. We're talking in the משנה Mishnah what we
taught in a ברייתא. braisa. אונס אשה מותר לישא בתה. Oneis isha
mutar liseis bita. So the ברייתא braisa makes it a little bit
more explicit. If a man בעל, ba'al, just rapes or in any
way sleeps with a woman, מותר לישא בתה, mutar liseis bita, he
is still permitted to marry Not only can't marry, can't sleep with
the daughter, which, so our משנה Mishnah is a little bit clearer
on that point. רמינהו, Reminehu, or he asks on this. הנחשד מן
האשה, Ha-nichshad min ha-ishah, somebody who is suspected of having an affair
with a woman. Whatever, he's single, she's single, doesn't matter. אסור באמה
ובבתה ובאחותה, Assur be-imah u-ve-vitah ve-achotah, and we won't let her him
marry this woman's mother, daughter, or sister. Why not? Okay, so there's
a rumor going around that this guy has been sleeping with with
with with Rachel. And now he says, but he proposes marriage to
Rachel's mother or to Rachel's daughter. We're not going to allow that.
Why not? There's no איסור, issur, we just taught in our משנה
there's no איסור. issur. Why do
you think we wouldn't want to allow him to marry Rachel's mother
or daughter? Doesn't look good. Yes, but there's a better reason also.
Not just doesn't look good. Because if he's been having an affair
with Rachel, then even after he marries the mother or daughter, he
might continue to carry on with Rachel. And if he carries on
with Rachel, that's the איסור דאורייתא, issur de-oraisa, right? Because now he's
married to a woman and he's sleeping with the woman's mother or
or daughter like his sister. עבירה, Aveira, but yes, but exactly. So
our משנה, our משנה doesn't seem to be bothered with the fact
that he could have been sleeping with a woman and then marrying
the mother, sister, and daughter. Again, not so at least rabbinically we
shouldn't allow it. So the גמרא Gemara? says, that's what the גמרא's
answer. מדרבנן, Mi-derabbanan, that's right, there's only rabbinic.
מדרבנן. Mi-derabbanan. וכל היכא דאיכא איסורא מדרבנן תני נושאין לכתחילה? Ve-chol heicha
de-ika issura mi-derabbanan tani nosin le-chatchilah? If there's a rabbinic prohibition,
would our משנה say you're allowed to marry the, you know, the
daughter or sister whatever of a woman a man slept with? Not
allowed, at least it's rabbinically forbidden. So the גמרא says, כי תנן
מתניתין לאחר מיתה, Ki tnan matnisin le-achar misah,
our משנה is that the woman that man slept with is now
dead. Okay, and now he can go ahead and marry her sister
or mother or daughter. Okay, and that's a big point I've left
out because now the point is so in terms of relationship so
it's a relationship that's only defined by having been related having been
a wife's, you know, mother daughter sister. In terms of a concern
that he's going to so that there was never a דאורייתא problem.
In terms of the rabbinic problem of you might continue to carry
on with her after the marriage and then he will be right
and then he'll be sleeping with this woman who is related to
woman number two that he's now married to,
that would not be a problem if woman number one is dead.
And therefore it's okay. Of course if woman number one is dead,
it would be מותר muttar even if he was really married to
her to sleep with the to marry the sister, right? That's the
funny thing, right? Because right the sister is married after the woman
after the wife dies, so it's not a anyway, but okay. But
that's the point. The basic point is that our משנה is talking
that biblically it's allowed. The ברייתא Baraisa introduces the fact that rabbinically
it's not allowed because of what it because then it could again.
It's okay to start if you start with the sexual relationship with
woman one and then marriage with woman two is not prohibited. But
marriage with woman one and then sex with woman two is. So
we don't allow rabbinically the first case because it'll turn into the
second case because then the woman he's married to then he'll continue
sleeping with the other woman and that is the prohibited case. Yes.
It would be helpful and could you say something about the word
אונס? ones? In other words like rape and sleeping around. I know
that's what I said. That at least the משנה says אנוסה ומפותה
anusah u-mefutah because those are the two examples in the Torah. You
know it's a I always say that the גמרא uses and the
משנה uses like, you know, הלכה and and legal terminology and in
the and in the Torah the only time you see I mean
I mean you have פילגש pilegesh so I could have talked about
that. But the basic cases where you see that the law deals
with acts of sex, you know, that are, you know, are outside
of marriage are either acts of rape or acts of seduction, אנוסה
ומפותה. anusah u-mefutah. כי יפתה איש בתולה אשר לא ארשה ושכב עמה
Ki yefateh ish betulah asher lo orasah ve-shachav imah etc. So when
the משנה wants to discuss sex outside of marriage, it discusses אנוסה
ומפותה, anusah u-mefutah, which is okay, but the problem that winds up
bothering me is that then we con then we simplify it made
so it was the first of the two terms to אנוסה תדי.
anusah tadi. That and we then by default talk about sex outside
of marriage always with as with the example of rape, which is
I just think it's disturbing. But that's what happens. I mean and
what's the difference between מפותה mefutah and אנוסה anusah in this in
this context? None. It's just that we you know however you describe
it all it means is a woman a man slept with outside
of marriage. That's all it means. Right whatever without knowing anything about
like the emotional interaction. That's right. Right. Okay, so now the גמרא
says like this: מנא הני מילי? Minani milei? Where do you get
this from? That it's defined that you first start with a relationship
of marriage and then the act of and then the act with
the other woman even an act of sex and not an act
of marriage is what's prohibited.
דתנו רבנן בכולהו נאמר שכיבה. De-tanu rabbanan be-chulah ne'emar shichivah. By all
the עריות arayos it says שכיבה, shichivah, right? Like you know לא
תשכב, lo tishkav, you know, it's always about לא תשכב lo tishkav
don't lie with meaning don't sleep with have an act of sex.
וכאן נאמר Ve-chan ne'emar this very phrase, sleep with, is our euphemism
for sex, which is the same thing as שכיבה, shichivah, right, just
means to lie down with. וכאן נאמר קיחה, Ve-khan ne'emar kichah, but
by the case of sister or mother or daughter it says לא
יקח. lo yikach. רש״י Rashi points to a פסוק, pasuk. איש כי
יקח את אשה ואת אמה. Ish ki yikach et ishah ve-et imah.
ואחותו לא תקח, ve-achoto lo tikach, don't marry. So marriage is an
important part of this equation. ואמרו לך דרך ליקוחין אסרה תורה, Ve-omru
lach derech likuchin asra torah, that it has to be about marriage.
Of course, if it has to be about marriage, you might say,
well, why doesn't it have to be about marrying both of them?
Marry the woman and her sister? Marry the woman and her mother?
Because the reason is because halakhically the marriage to the sister or
the marriage to the mother won't take effect. You're already married to
the woman, right, then a marriage with an עריות arayot will not
be binding. So since it says קיחה kichah we have to start
with a marriage, and since however then the second relationship can't be
a marriage, that we define as just an act
of sex. אמר ליה רבא לאביי, Amar lei Rava le-Abaye, אלא מעתה
גבי אחותו דכתיב, ela me-atah gabbi achoto de-chtiv, by the sister it
says, איש אשר יקח את אחותו בת אביו או בת אמו, ish
asher yikach et achoto bat aviv o vat imo, he takes his
sister, right? הכא נמי דרך קיחה הוא דאסרה תורה דרך שכיבה שרי?
Hacha nami derech kichah hu de-asrah torah derech shichivah sharei? So there
sister, and it's also כי יקח, ki yikach, would we say it's
only אסור asur if a man marries his sister? אמר ליה ליקוחין
כתיבא בתורה סתם. Amar lei likuchin ketivah be-torah stam. The Torah says
take, which is generic, it could mean marriage, it could mean sex.
Now we will have, we will, we will rather interpret it as
marriage, that's the more simple explanation of this. ראוי לקיחה, Ra'uy likichah,
if it's dealing with a woman in which marriage is possible, then
it means קיחה, kichah, then it means marriage. So when it's dealing
with a wife and then a wife's sister, wife's mother, we'll say
the first marriage wife is literally wife. But ראוי לשכיבה ra'uy lishchivah
by the case of sister where marriage isn't possible, in that case
what קיחה kichah means is שכיבה shichivah is sex. Okay, so it's
not so גלאט glatt as we would say, because קיחה kichah doesn't
always mean that it's about marriage, okay, but in cases where it's
possibly about marriage, that's how we're going to interpret it. Here's a
terminology, חכמים chachamim could have used the word שכובה shchuvah instead of
אנוסה. anusah. I guess. But again, it was never,
maybe, okay, but it was never interpreted. רבא אמר, Rava amar, אנוסת
אשה מותר לישא בתה. anusat ishah mutar lisa bitah. If a man
rapes, and there again you get rape, not just sleep with, a
woman, he can marry the daughter. מהכא, Me-hacha, you get that from
this פסוק. pasuk כתיב ערות בת בנך או בת בתך לא תגלה,
Ketiv ervat bat bincha o vat bitcha lo tegaleh, do not expose
the nakedness of your granddaughter. הבת בנו דידך ובת בתך דידך, Habat
bino didach ve-bat bitcha didach, if it was your wife's granddaughter and
not yours, you weren't biologically related to her, גלי, galei, it sounds
like that would be a problem. וכתיב, U-chtiv, but another verse says,
ערות אשה ובתה לא תגלה את בת בנה ואת בת בתה לא
תקח, ervat ishah u-vitah lo tegaleh et bat benah ve-et bat bitah
lo tikach, that you cannot, that a man can't have sex with
his wife's granddaughter, even if it's not his. So which is it?
Is wife's granddaughter okay or not okay? הא כיצד? Ha ketsad? כאן
באונסין כאן בנשואין. Kan be-onsin kan be-nisuin. It depends whether he's married
to the woman. If he's married to the woman, then his wife's
granddaughter is forbidden because it's his wife's granddaughter. If he's not married
to the woman, it's just a woman he had sex with, then
if it's this woman's granddaughter
but not his granddaughter, he's allowed, because he's not, you understand, because
it's not any step-relationship. He's not married here. איפכא אנא, Ibecha ana,
why don't I say the reverse? Why don't I say that if
it's a woman he סתם stam had sex with, and this, you
know, תוספות Tosafot is a little ironic that we would be more
מחמיר machmir with outside of marriage, but תוספות Tosafot is no, maybe
exactly like the point Davis said, more licentiousness. So סתם stam a
woman a guy sleeps with outside of marriage, maybe there the granddaughter
will be forbidden, the woman's granddaughter will be forbidden, but maybe in
marriage not? איפכא אנא? Ibecha ana? No. עריות שאר כתיב בהו. Arayot
she'er ketiv behu. It says שארה הנה, she'erah henah, which is שאר
she'er means flesh, means a type of a biological relationship. So בנשואין
איכא שאר. be-nisuin ika she'er. When there's marriage, okay, through a, you
know, one degree removed, it's a step relationship, but you can talk
about שאר, she'er, like some type of a, you know, they're relatives
to some degree. ובאונסין ליכא שאר. U-ve-onsin leka she'er. In a case
where it was just a woman a man slept with and it's
her granddaughter, so it's not his biological granddaughter, it's not a step-granddaughter,
so it would never be described as שאר, she'er, שארה הנה, she'erah
henah,
which has to do with some degree of being a relative. Okay,
so anyway, from one way or another we know that it starts
with marriage in the case of wife, wife's mother, daughter, sister, and
then the, but then the forbidden thing is then an act of
sex after that, not an act of marriage, because marriage isn't possible
once it is one of the עריות. arayot. And the same about
father's wife or son's wife, it starts with being wife. רבי יוסי
אסר באנוסת אביו. Rabbi Yose asar be-anusat aviv. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says
by the case of father, even if it's not father's wife, just
a woman the father slept with, also forbidden.
אמר רב גידל אמר רב, Amar Rav Gidel amar Rav, מאי טעמא
דרבי יהודה? mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehudah? דכתיב לא יקח איש את אשת
אביו ולא יגלה כנף אביו. De-chtiv lo yikach ish et eshet aviv
ve-lo yigaleh knaf aviv. A man can't marry his wife's father, his
step-mother, and cannot reveal the hem of the father. So what does
this mean? כנף שראה אביו, Knaf she-ra'ah aviv, like hem of the
shirt The hem of the skirt that his father saw it, right,
we had this way earlier, meaning, you know, the nakedness that his
father, the woman that his father saw her nakedness, the woman that
his father had sex with, לא יגלה, lo yegaleh, he cannot have
sex with that woman, okay, even if it's not his stepmother. ומימאי
דבאנוסה כתיב, umaimai de'banussa ketiv, again, once again, calling her אנוסה, anussa,
right, לא שכובה lo shechuva as אבא דב Abba Dov suggested or
even משודלת. meshudelet. Anyway, how do we know that it's talking about
a woman outside of marriage, let's say it that way, דכתיב מעילא
קרא, dechativ me'ila kara, because an earlier פסוק pasuk says, or a
good number of פסוקים psukim earlier, ונתן האיש השוכב עמה לאבי הנערה
חמשים כסף. venatan ha'ish hashochev imma la'avi hana'ara chamishim kasef. Okay, so
that's a case of rape, that's a case of אנוסה. anussa. So
that earlier part, earlier, earlier, you know, פסוקים, psukim, inform that this
case is also talking about a woman outside of marriage, like that's
a case a man rapes a woman and he marries her and
he pays the father and so forth. ורבנן, ve'rabanan, the Rabbis say
that, אי הוה סמיך ליה כדקאמרת, ei hava samich leh kedekamarat, if
that was immediately juxtaposed, I would have conceded the point, but השתא
דלא סמיך ליה, hashta d'lo samich leh, but those פסוקים psukim about
rape or whatever are way earlier, so מיבעי ליה לכדרב ענן. miba'ei
leh lechiderav anan. I don't read the פסוק pasuk the way you
read it, that it's about a woman the father slept with, I
read the פסוק like רב ענן Rav Anan reads it. דאמר רב
ענן אמר שמואל, de'amar Rav Anan amar Shmuel, בשומרת יבם של אביו
הכתוב מדבר. beshomeret yavam shel aviv hakatuv medaber. When it says לא
יגלה כנף אביו, lo yegaleh knaf aviv, it doesn't mean any woman
the father slept with, it means a woman who is in a
quasi-marriage relationship with the father. What's a quasi-marriage relationship with the father?
שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam, זיקה. So the father has now has an
obligation to do יבום or חליצה with this woman, he's quasi-married to
her, that's also being prohibited, but not סתם stam a woman that
the father slept with. ומאי כנף אביו? umai knaf aviv? כנף הראויה
לאביו, knaf harauya l'aviv, the woman who is fit to be the
father's wife, not just סתם stam a woman that the father slept
with. ולא יגלה. velo yegaleh. So the גמרא says, ותיפוק ליה משום
דודתו? vetipok leh mishum dodato? I don't get it. If it's a
woman his father has to do יבום or חליצה with, then it's
his aunt, right? The father's brother's wife. So that's already ערווה, erva,
that's biblically prohibited, and that's an איסור כרת. issur karet. Right? It's
not clear that would they have said that, you know, this prohibition
is an איסור כרת? issur karet? A woman the father slept with
or a שומרת יבם? shomeret yavam? Doesn't sound like from other סוגיות
sugyot that we're talking about an איסור כרת. issur karet. We're talking
about maybe an additional לאו. lav. Okay, but this woman is actually
an aunt and it's
an איסור כרת. issur karet. לעבור עליו בשני לאוין. la'avor alav bishnei
lavin. Alright, so give him another לאו. lav. ותיפוק ליה משום יבמה
לשוק? vetipok leh mishum yevama lashuk? Okay, this woman is also forbidden
not just because it's the father, the woman the father had to
do יבום, any woman that is waiting יבום is forbidden to another
man, right? We've been discussing that. Alright, לעבור עליו בשלושה לאוין. la'avor
alav bishlosha lavin. Get him three times. ואיבעית אימא לאחר מיתה. ve'iba'it
eima le'achar mita. Or maybe it is after the father dies. So
after the father dies, she's no longer a יבמה לשוק yevama lashuk
because she no longer needs יבום or חליצה, there was only one
brother, but she still is father's brother's wife, she still is aunt,
but we give another לאו lav because it's also the woman that
the father had some זיקה with, some relationship. And he says, לעבור
עליו בשלושה לאוין? la'avor alav bishlosha lavin? Yes, definitely. Okay, the גמרא
does this. Now, that was the debate. Now the גמרא is going
to turn to have a fun time here. This is the type
of a גמרא that Shalom Carmy once said many years ago, sort
of, this is what the Rabbis did before they had TV.
And these are going to be little brain teasers about, can you
figure out what the relationship here is? Like or what the answer
to this little, to this little brain teaser is, all about like
how somebody's related to somebody else. So let's take a look. And
we used to say that the entire מסכת masechet is brain... Well,
you'll see a special case of it right now.
Alright. אחי מאב ולא מאם, achi me'av velo me'em, somebody is
a brother on the father's side and not on the mother's side
of this woman,
והוא בעלה דאם, vehu ba'ala de'em, and he is the husband of
the mother, ואנא ברתא דאיתתיה, va'ana barta de'ittateh, and I am the
daughter of his wife. Okay, so that was clear enough. So what
does this mean? Let's look at רש"י. Rashi. I figured this out
last night, but I always have to renew it. So רש"י Rashi
says, the second line in רש"י, Rashi, אחי מאבי ונשא את אמי.
achi me'avi venasa et immi. Alright, so now we're going to have
to do this.
Yep.
Okay, so אחי מאבי, achi me'avi, right,
נשא את אמי. nasa et immi. Okay, so this is her mother,
not related to him, right? So this is his, right, what is
this, his step-sister, no, half-sister's mother. Okay, so he married the mother.
אחי מאבי ונשא את אמי, achi me'avi venasa et immi, so אחי
מאב ולא מאם והוא בעלה דאם, achi me'av velo me'em vehu ba'ala
de'em, married my mother, ואנא ברתא דאיתתיה, va'ana barta de'ittateh, I am
the daughter of his wife. I am my half-brother's
step-daughter.
Right? Okay, fine. That was... That was the easy one. This is
going to get only harder from here. Okay. אמר רמי בר חמא,
Amar Rami bar Chama, דלא כרבי יהודה, d'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda, that's not
like Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, דמתניתין d'matnitin of our Mishnah. Why is it
not like Rabbi Yehuda of our
Mishnah? Because, wait, why is it not like Rabbi Yehuda of our
Mishnah? ונשא ראובן את אנוסת אביו. Venasa Reuven et anusat aviv. Wait,
hold on. אחי מאבי נשא את אמי, Achi me'avi nasa et imi,
היינו דיעקב אנס את אימא Hynu d'Yaakov anas et ima והוליד בת
v'holid bat
ונשא ראובן. venasa Reuven. Oh right, because yes, yes, yes, because because
the father here could this she the daughter here it came from
came from the right from the father and the mother, right? So
but they couldn't have been married, right? Because if he had been
married to her, then the son could never have married his stepmother.
So it only works if he wasn't married to her, and even
that and even that works only not according to Rabbi Yehuda, okay?
Yeah. All right. All right. דלא כרבי יהודה דמתניתין. d'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda
d'matnitin. Now here's that was the easy one. Here's tough. אחוהי וברהי,
Achi v'breih, he is a brother and he is my son. אחתיה
אנא, Achateih ana, I am his sister. דהאי דדרינא אכתפאי d'hai d'darina
aktephai and I am the sister
of of of my son, of the one that I'm carrying on
my shoulders. Okay? So this my son here is basically it's saying
my son is my son is my brother. Okay? Got that? That
was a complicated way of saying my son is my brother. He's
my brother, he's my son, I am the sister of the one
that I'm carrying on my shoulders. My son is my brother. How
do you get my son is my brother? It sounds like an
Oedipal... משכחת לה בעובד כוכבים הבא על בתו. Mishkachat la b'oved kochavim
haba al bito. From this point on we're going to deal with
things that can only work in a case of incest. So when
we want to describe it we're going to say that it was
a non-Jew who did it. We don't want to say that a
Jew was engaged in this type of incest. So here's the scenario:
A non-Jew, okay, what? In the Chinatown's terms. Yeah, just thinking it
back. Play no spoilers. All right, anyway. Okay. בעובד כוכבים הבא על
בתו. B'oved kochavim haba al bito. Okay,
so a non-Jew, a non-Jew, right, has sex whatever, somebody has sex
with his daughter. So the child, right, is the mother's son and
the mother's brother, right? Because right because it was from the right
because he had sex with the father so it's mother's son and
her brother. שלום לך חברי ברא דאנת אמי, Shalom lach chavri b'ra
d'ant imi, my son. בר אחתיה אנא, Bar achateih ana, I am
your the daughter of your sister. Okay? So the woman's son is
the sister's
no, no wait. שלום לך חברי, Shalom lach chavri, right the woman's
son is the right the mother is right the sister's daughter. How
does that work? What? Right, so משכחת לה בעובד כוכבים הבא על
בת בתו. mishkachat la b'oved kochavim haba al bat bito. Okay, somebody
had sex with his granddaughter. So here you have grandfather, father, daughter.
He had sex with his granddaughter. So the child here is what?
So what is it? This child is also this woman's grandfather's daughter,
which is this woman's right this woman's aunt, right? Is that right?
Her daughter is also if it's a grandfather's daughter, right that means
it's a father's sister. Her daughter is her father's sister. Is that
clear? Yes? You guys with me? Yeah. Okay. שלום לך חברי, Shalom
lach chavri, that works. Okay, so let's read that again. שלום לך
חברי בת אחתך אנא. Shalom lach chavri bat achatech ana. I am
right I am your the daughter of your well okay so this
is a woman this is a mother. So I am the daughter
of so here this guy I am the daughter of your sister,
right because this guy is also up here,
right because yes? So I am the daughter of your sister. Okay,
you're my aunt. Okay, moving on. So so she's making these statements
showing her how it's possible. Exactly. These were riddles. Okay. Okay. דליי
דדלו דבלא, d'lay d'dalu davla, so it's a funny thing right it
means like this was a riddle said to the people who water
the fields or Tosafot says it's a poetic way of referring to
Talmidei Chachamim, okay? ריפו בחוסטר פתר, ripu b'chuster peter, let fall among
you this is like a whole introduction like this hidden explanation like
here's a riddle let me riddle you a riddle. דהאי דדרינא, d'hai
d'darina, the one that I am carrying, meaning my son, okay, הוא
בר, hu bar, he is a son, ואנא ברת אחוהי, v'ana brat
achoveih, and I am the daughter of a brother or of a
sibling. So what does that mean? Let's give the answer and then
we'll work it out. משכחת לה בעובד כוכבים הבא על בת בנו.
Mishkachat la b'oved kochavim haba al bat bno. Okay, so similar case
except it was not bat bito, it was bat bno, what I
said first. So the case was he is a son, okay, I
mean I guess this is a son here, he is a son...
הוא
בר ואנא ברת אחוה hu bar va'ana brat achuhe and I am,
because this guy's also up here, the daughter of his brother. It's
basically the same thing, okay? Except it's it's with a it's with
a father in the mix rather than a mother in the mix.
Okay, I did one more, I think one more.
בייא בייא וו וו מאח baia baia wo wo me'ach regarding my
brother הוא אב hu av and he's a father והוא בעל v'hu
ba'al and he's a husband, brother, father and husband והוא בר בעל
v'hu bar ba'al and he is a husband's son והוא בעלה דאמי
v'hu ba'ala d'ime and a stepfather ואנא ברתא דאיתתיה va'ana barta d'it'tei
and I am his wife's daughter. Well that's the same thing as
stepfather. ולא so this guy has all these relationships ולא יהיב פיתא
לאחוהי יתמי בני ברתיה v'lo yeihiv pita l'achoi yasmei b'nei barta and
he won't even feed the
brothers who's the orphan brothers who are the son of his daughter.
All right, so let's figure it out and then we'll work it
backwards. So משפחת לה בעובדי כוכבים המבעל אמו mishpachas la b'ovei kochavim
hamaba'al imo והוליד ממנה בת. v'holi minah bat. Okay this is what
happened.
So here's a man, okay, who has sex with his mother and
now he's got a daughter. So this daughter is now what? This
daughter is now his daughter and his sister. So he's got a
daughter and a sister.
והוליד ממנה בת v'holi minah bat where were we? וחזר ובעל אותה
בת v'chazar uva'al oto bat
then he goes and has sex with her daughter. Okay וחזר ובעל
אותה
בת v'chazar uva'al oto bat וחזר זקן ובעלה והוליד ממנה בנים v'chazar
zakein uva'alah v'holi minah banim and then the one minute
one minute the grandfather
had sex with the daughter?
No. So he has sex with her and then he has a
son, okay and then the זקן zakein is I think him, right?
Because he's now the right? I think so. וחזר זקן v'chazar zakein
I think I'm getting this right. No maybe not.
I figured this out last night. ובעלה והוליד ממנה בנים uva'alah v'holi
minah banim let's take a look. How does this work? Let's figure
this out. I thought the grandfather was the person's father, this guy's
father, who's the grandfather that daughter he had illicitly. And then he
has sex with her and has sex with would be the next
generation.
It's the granddaughter. No, the זקן zakein really because it was only
I think it was with I think it's with this. I think
it's with this daughter. Yeah. So let's see if this works. And
now how does this work? Let's see if this parses. Okay so
I've got a brother so Rashi says like this וקאמר הך בת
של אביה הכי. v'ka'amar hach bat shel aviha hachi. So this daughter
is saying the following. Okay דהוא אחיה מן האם. d'hu achiya min
ha'em.
So this guy here is my is my brother, right? That we
established right away, right? He had sex with mother, so he's my
brother, okay מן האם min ha'em וגם אביה v'gam aviha he's my
brother and my father, that was the first thing we figured out
ובעלה u'va'alah oh
and he's my husband because since then he had sex with her
we're he's referring to him as husband. So this guy is my
father, my brother and my husband. Biologically father and brother, right? And
then he had sex with her, so he's my husband. So this
guy is my father, my brother and my husband. Okay ובן בעלה
u'ben ba'alah
and he is my also the the son of my husband because
since the grandfather his father had sex with me I'm considering his
father my husband as well. So not only is he my father,
brother and husband, he's also my husband son. Okay because this is
also a father ובן בעלה. u'ben ba'alah. Okay so that and and
so that's how we get that scenario. And he's not feeding him.
And he's not feeding him, right. He's got all these relationships not
feeding him anyway. Okay last one. All right.
אנא ואת אחין ana v'at achin where am I?
אנא ואת אחין ana v'at achin you and I are siblings. אנא
ואבוך אחין ana v'avuch achin you and your father you and your
father and I are siblings. אנא ואימך אחין ana v'imach achin your
mother and I are siblings.
So משפחת לה בעובדי כוכבים המבעל אמו והוליד ממנה שתי בנות. mishpachas
la b'ovei kochavim hamaba'al imo v'holi minah shtei banot. עובדי כוכבים המבעל
אמו ovei kochavim hamaba'al imo and watch TV? והוליד ממנה שתי בנות.
v'holi minah shtei banot. Okay so we had two girls. Okay right
and you thought cable TV was a problem. Okay these two girls
are his sisters and daughters. Okay והוליד ממנה שתי בנות v'holi minah
shtei banot וחזר ובעל אחת מהן והוליד ממנה בן. v'chazar uva'al achat
meihen v'holi minah ben.
And then he has sex with one of them and has a
son וקריא ליה אחותה
דאמי v'karya lei achata d'imei and calls him the the his mother's
sister. One minute
hold on. וקאמרה ליה אחות אימו אנא. Vekamrah lei achos imo ana.
Oh, so she says to him. Okay, so she wait, no, she
who says to who? I think she, the sister-wife. No, she says
to him. Let's take a look. וקאמרה ליה אחות אימו אנא, Vekamrah
lei achos imo ana,
I am your sister. Okay, that we got. ואת אחי מאב אחד,
Ve'at achi me'av echad,
and you are... no, she is saying to him, wait, and you
are my... you're
my sister. Right. Wait, wait.
וקאמרה ליה אחות אימו אנא, Vekamrah lei achos imo ana, I am
your sister.
אנא ואת אחי מאב אחד... Ana ve'at achi me'av echad... Huh? No,
that's the next
case. Am I in the next case? Yeah, they skipped something. Okay.
The period is after וקאמר ליה. Vekamar lei. Skip one back to
the and that's another case. וקרי ליה. Vekarei lei. Right. Okay. וקרי
ליה. Vekarei lei. Right. We have another case starting from שתי בנות
חזרה בעל אחת מהן והוליד הימנה בן וקרי ליה אחתה דאימיה Shetei
banot chazra ba'al achat mehen veholid himenah ben vekarei lei achatei de'imei
וקאמר ליה הכי. Vekamar lei hachi.
Okay,
fine. And now, so how does that work? So what is he
saying? He's saying is, who's saying to who?
She's saying to him that you and I are אנא ואת אחי.
Ana ve'at achi.
You and I are siblings. אנא ואבוך אחי. Ana ve'avuch achi. You
and your father, I and your father are siblings, right?
Who is saying to who? She's saying to him? Yes. Okay, she
is saying to him. You and I are siblings because we have
the same father. Yes? You and I are siblings.
אנא ואבוך אחי. Ana ve'avuch achi. I and your father are siblings,
right? Because they have the same mother. Right? Remember the father had
sex, they were sisters here. You and I are siblings, you and
your father are siblings. אנא ואימך אחי. Ana ve'imach achi. And you
and your mother are, I and your mother are siblings. Okay, fine.
Alright, that was that. אנא ואימך, Ana ve'imach, fine. Okay,
moving on.
Okay. אנא ואת בני אחי. Ana ve'at benei achi.
You and I, this is the easiest one. You and I are
siblings, you know, from brothers. Children of siblings? Children of siblings, I'm
sorry. Right, cousins. בני אחי. Benei achi. Right, we're cousins. אנא ואבוך
בני אחי. Ana ve'avuch benei achi. First cousins.
I and your father are cousins. אנא ואימך בני אחי. Ana ve'imach
benei achi. First cousins. So the גמרא says: הבתא נמי משכחת לה.
Habita nami mishkachat lah. Oh,
we can get that one without even a ראיה. What? כגון, Kegon,
we don't have to say an אנן anan here, we can say
Reuven. כגון ראובן שיש לו שתי בנות. Kegon Reuven sheyesh lo shetei
banot. Okay, Reuven has, alright, Reuven has two daughters.
Reuven has two daughters. Okay, שתי בנות. Shetei banot. And what does
he do? כגון ראובן
ואתא שמעון ונסיב חדא מנייהו. Kegon Reuven ve'ata Shimon venasiv chada mineihu.
Shimon comes and marries a niece, which he's allowed to do. ואתא
בר לוי Ve'ata bar Levi and Levi's son comes ונסיב חדא מנייהו
Venasiv chada mineihu marries the other one. And in that case, וקאמר
ליה בריה דשמעון לבר בריה דלוי, Vekamar lei bereih deShimon levar bereih
deLevi, and the son of Shimon here, right, says, son of Shimon
to the grandson of Levi, says this to Levi's grandson. So what
is he saying to Levi's grandson? He is saying one more time:
I and your father are cousins. So I and your father, right,
are cousins because your father is, that's true, because he's Shimon's son
and his father is Levi's son. So I and your father are
cousins. אנא ואת בני אחי. Ana ve'at benei achi. אנא ואבוך בני
אחי. Ana ve'avuch benei achi. I and your father are cousins.
I just did that. Oh, first, we're cousins because we have mothers
who are sisters. I and your father are cousins, we just did
that. And I and your mother are cousins because, why is I
cousins with your mother? Oh, because of Shimon's son and Reuven's daughter.
They're first cousins or first cousins? Okay, so we've got it all
done. So if everybody has to leave, you can leave, but I
just need to show you this one thing. It's for two minutes,
but if you've got to go, you've got to go. But has
anybody ever heard of the song, I Am My Own Grandpa? Yeah,
yeah. נו, Nu, when I was 23,
I was married to a widow who was pretty as
can be. This widow had a grown-up daughter who had hair of
red. My father fell in love with her and soon they, too,
were wed. This made my dad my son-in-law and changed my very
life. My daughter was my mother cause she was my father's wife.
To complicate the matter, even though it brought me joy, I soon
became the father of a bouncing baby boy.
My little baby then became a brother-in-law to dad, and so became
my uncle, though it made me very sad. For if he was
my uncle, then that also made him brother of the widow's grown-up
daughter who of course was my
stepmother. Father's wife then had a son, kept him on the run,
and he became my grandchild, for he was my daughter's son. My
wife is now my mother's mother, and it makes me blue, because
although she is my wife, she's my grandmother too.
If my wife is my grandmother, then I'm her grandchild, and every
time I think of it, it nearly drives me wild. For now
I have become the strangest case you ever saw. As husband of
my grandmother, I am my own grandpa! You have to send that
out to us! Alright. But what do you know, though, the proper
ending to our גמרא? It was all בהיתר. beheter. Alright. So we'll
stop there. Although in most states at present can't marry.